Jersey City, N.J. First Congregational Church records, 1859-1972.
Congregational Library & Archives
Jersey City, N.J. First Congregational Church records, 1859-1972.
RG0723
Congregational Library & Archives
2.39 Cubic Feet
(5 boxes, 1 folder)
The First Congregational Church in Jersey City, New Jersey, was first gathered in 1841 though it was not until 1858 that the church was formally organized. The first church building, called the Tabernacle Church, was constructed in 1863. A new church building was purchased in 1896 and a new church was constructed in 1904. Due to declining membership, the church was dissolved in 1970. This collection contains records related to the administration, history, and membership of the First Congregational Church. The records include meeting minutes, correspondence, legal documents, vital records, and ministerial records.
First Congregational Church (Jersey City, N.J.)
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
No acquisition information is available for this collection.
Historical Note
The First Congregational Church in Jersey City, New Jersey, was first gathered in 1841 by a group of people originally from New England. However, due to the church's support of abolition, the church did not flourish and and may have temporarily dissolved in the convening years. A new effort to gather a church was begun in 1857 and the First Congregational Church was formally organized on April 14, 1858. Services were variously held at rented locations throughout Jersey City including Lyceum Hall, Park Hall, Metropolitan Hall, Franklin Hall, Hedding Methodist Episcopal Church, and a former Unitarian church building. The church's first church building was constructed in 1963 and was called the Tabernacle Church.
In 1896, following growth in church membership, the church purchased the South Bergen Reformed Church and the land it was on. On this site, a new church building was constructed in 1904. Land was also purchased across the road from the site in 1900 and on that land the People's Palace, a community center, was built.
By the 1960s the church's membership was waning and in 1970 the church officially dissolved.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains records related to the administration and history of the First Congregational Church in Jersey City, New Jersey, as well as records related to the members of the church. The collection includes record book and records of meetings, important vital records for members of the church, financial records, records related to the church building, legal and governance documents, and records related to the ministers of the church.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into the three series listed below. Within each series, materials have been organized first by chronological order and then by topic so that closely related materials are listed in sequence.
Series 1: Administrative records, 1859-1972
Series 2: Membership records, 1898-1972
Series 3: Ministerial records, 1910-1970
Technical Requirements
A cassette reader is required in order to access cassette materials.
Baptismal records.; Church buildings.; Church finance.; Church membership.; Church records and registers.; Clergy -- Appointment, call, and election.; Contracts for deeds; Deacons -- Congregational churches.; Jersey City (N.J) -- Church history.; Legal documents.; Marriage records.; First Congregational Church (Jersey City, N.J.)
- Administrative records, 1859 1972; 1859-1972; 36 Files; 4 Volumes; 1 Cassettes
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains records related to the administration and organization of the First Congregational Church in Jersey City, New Jersey. This series includes church records, meeting minutes, legal documents, correspondence, annual reports, wills and bequests, governance records, financial records, and records related to the church's buildings and property.
  - Governance records, 1859 1966; 1859-1966 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Deeds and mortgages, 1896 1942; 1896-1942 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Church records, 1897 1944; 1897-1944 (Box 2, Volume 1)
  - Miscellaneous building records, 1897 1969; 1897-1941, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Miscellaneous financial records, 1902 1951; 1902-1951 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Legal documents, 1908 1950; 1908-1950 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Trustee's communications, 1914 1933; 1914-1933 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Trustee's communications, 1915 1941; 1915-1941 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Special programs, 1916 1917; 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Renovations, 1916 1924; 1916-1924 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Wills and bequests, 1925 1957; 1925-1957 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Board of trustees minutes, 1925 1943; 1925-1943 (Box 5, Volume 1)
  - Board of trustees minutes, 1943 1945; 1943-1945 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Board of trustees minutes, 1946 1950; 1946-1950 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Board of trustees minutes, 1951 1954; 1951-1954 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Board of trustees minutes, 1955 1958; 1955-1958 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Board of trustees minutes, 1959 1965; 1959-1962, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Board of deacons minutes, 1927 1935; 1927-1935 (Box 1, Volume 1)
  - Board of deacons minutes, 1935 1947; 1935-1947 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Separated Materials
    Loose materials from this volume were separated and placed in the folder Board of Deacon's minutes, 1948-1952.
  - Board of deacons records, 1948 1952; 1948-1952 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Materials in this folder were removed from the Board of Deacons minutes, 1935-1947, volume. Original order has been maintained.
  - Board of deacons minutes, 1956 1958; 1956-1958 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Board of deacon's minutes, 1959 1965; 1959-1965 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Society minutes, 1932 1953; 1932-1953 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Society financial reports, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Society meetings, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Clerk's correspondence, 1942 1971; 1942-1971 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Clerk's correspondence, 1961 1972; 1961-1972 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Church meeting minutes, 1944 1949; 1944-1949 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Church meeting minutes, 1951 1957; 1951-1957 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Church meeting minutes, 1960 1970; 1960-1970 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Annual reports, 1950 1955; 1950-1955 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Annual reports, 1956 1959; 1956-1959 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Annual reports, 1960 1964; 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Annual reports, 1965 1969; 1965-1969 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Histories, 1951, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Renovations, 1960 1961; 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Church mergers, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Council minutes, 1966 1970; 1966-1970 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Tabernacle Congregational Church separation, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Committee of 20 report, undated (Box 5, Cassette 1)
  - Main floor seating chart, undated (Folder 6)
- Membership records, 1898 1972; 1898-1972; 14 Folders
  This series contains records related to the members of the First Congregational Church in Jersey City, New Jersey. This series includes vital records such as records of marriages, deaths, baptisms, admissions, and dismissions.
  - Vital records, 1898 1951; 1898-1951 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Vital records, 1899 1969; 1899-1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Dismissions, 1898 1966; 1898-1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Dismissions, 1939 1942; 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Dismissions, 1942 1945; 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Marriage records, 1908 1968; 1908-1968 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Marriage records, 1920 1937; 1920-1937 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Membership records, 1913 1963; 1913-1963 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Admissions, 1915 1917; 1915-1917 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Year book reports, 1929 1940; 1929-1940 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous vital and membership records, 1941 1972; 1941-1972 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Membership list, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Membership correspondence, 1951 1960; 1951-1960 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Paul R. Hunter marriage and funeral records, 1957 1967; 1957-1967 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Ministerial records, 1910 1970; 1910-1970; 9 Folders; 1 Object
  This series contains records related to the ministers of the First Congregational Church in Jersey City, New Jersey. The biographical files contain correspondence, programs, photographs, and other documents related to their time as minister at the church.
  - Hary L. Everett biographical files, 1910 1940; 1910, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Ben F. Wyland biographical files, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Llewelyn Arnold Owen biographical files, 1941 1946; 1941-1946 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Herman Van Lunen biographical files, 1946 1952; 1946-1952 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - William Nisbet biographical files, 1947, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Sprigg Harwood biographical files, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Paul Hunter biographical files, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - James E. Linter biographical files, 1963 1966; 1963-1966 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Russell D. Custer biographical files, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - John L. Scudder bookplate, undated (Box 5, Object 1)